Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company
plans are not the first choice of most policy holders
initially.  But
as we compare the plans of different companies,
we come to know that
HDFC plans are very expensive
and the standalone companies like Star,
NV, CK, Health Insurance, their plans are
cheap but there are a lot of complaints
or these companies are not good in terms of service.
And because of these two reasons,
Aditya Birla has a sweet
spot that many policy
holders end up buying these plus.  And it is
not that the plans of this company are not good.
You get very good coverage at a very reasonable
premium.  But the most
important question is
how is this company in terms of claims?  Because
our purpose of buying health insurance is
not to keep this PDF safe.  We
want someone from our family to be
admitted tomorrow.  If someone needs money
for treatment, the company should pay the claim amount.  To
check this, in today's report
card video, we will see
how many people's health claims have been approved by Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company till the latest financial year 2025-26 i.e. till 31 March 2026.
How many people's
claims have been rejected?  Out of the claimed
amount, how much money has been paid by this company
and how much amount has been rejected
and also how many policy holders had to
complain during the claim and also you will
know at what speed this
company settled the claims within the last year.
If you have watched the
first two videos in the Health Insurance Report Card series,
you will be
familiar with these three disclaimers.  But
I would definitely like to tell these three things to the viewers who have come for the first time.  The
data I will be using in this video is
pure health insurance data.
That does not include personal accident and travel
insurance figures.
Secondly, the source of this data
is the insurance company's public disclosure document,
which is still listed on the company's website.
If you want to verify the data
or check other data,
you can check it from the insurance company's website.
And thirdly, in the Health Insurance
Report Card series, I
score, rate and grade different companies based on their performance in each video.
So this method of grading, this
method of scoring is Insurance Impact's own
methodology.  Because no such
benchmark or any standard method is
available in the industry.  So, let's
start the video.  Friends, in this video review,
we will use a total of five metrics.  The
company will be measured on five parameters.
Our first parameter will be the
claim settlement ratio.  This will tell us
how many claims were filed pan India in Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company in the latest financial year 2025-26 and
how many of those claims were settled by the company.
Settled means approved.
We will also find out the percentage of claims that have not been settled.  Now to calculate the claim settlement
ratio, we need to have some data.  There should be
some figures regarding the claim
numbers.  Let's take a look at them.
Total claims filed in this financial year were
2963880
claims.  This is the total number of claims filed.
But there were some claims which were
outstanding at the end of the last financial year
i.e. were in process.  So that too has been
settled during this financial year.  So
that number was 4685
claims.  So we have added these also
because the company might have taken a decision on these claims
also in this financial year.
And when this financial year ends,
that is on 31 March 2026, some
claims still remain outstanding which will be
closed in the next financial year.
We will subtract such claims from this figure
because the company has not yet taken any decision on them.
And that number is 22487
claims.  After adjusting these, the total
adjusted claims filed
in this financial year were 2988248
claims.  And how many claims have been settled?
claims were settled.  The
formula to calculate the claim settlement ratio is total claims
settled.  The number of claims for which the company has
paid money will be divided by the
total claims filed
after adjusting the outstanding
claims and multiplied by 100.  So the number
comes out to be 97.26%,
which means the company has approved 97 out of 100 claims.
Three claims have been rejected.
If you want to know
how many claims the company has resolved in the entire year,
then subtract the figure of settled claims from the total number of claims.
This number comes to approximately 82,000.
If you get the exact number then please do let
me know by commenting.
Now friends, let's talk about what this
claim settlement ratio is like?  This
is very wonderful because you know the
criteria we have set is that if the
claim settlement ratio of a company is more than 95%
then that company will be in the
excellent category.  If someone's score is 90 to 95
then we will put him in the good category
and if it is between 85 to 90 then he will
come in the average category.  But Aditya Birla's
claim settlement ratio is 97.2%, which
means the company is settling a lot of claims.
Only 2.75 i.e. only two out of 100
or you can say three claims have been
made by the company.  Rejected in the
past financial year.  We have come to know that what is the
total number of claims that have been settled.
But the claims paid ratio, which is our
second metric.  This will tell us
how much money the company has paid.  When
policy holders asked for ₹100,
how much of that amount has the company given
across India in the last year.  And from this we will be
able to know that the number of claim settlements of the company is
quite good.  Is
this company also great in terms of giving money.
I have also calculated the figures for you to calculate the claims paid ratio and
I have also converted them into crores.
Because this was given in lakhs in the data.
So it was quite difficult to understand him.   The
total amount paid by the company
in the claims form last year is ₹3522
crore.  ₹3522
crore worth of claims were paid in
financial year 2025-26 by Aditya Birla
Health Insurance Company but
how much claim money was demanded by the policy holders, that
amount was ₹4200 crore, some claims
money was outstanding which had to be paid
from the previous financial year and some
was outstanding at the end of this financial year as well,
both were almost equal ₹17 crore,
after adjusting these the total claim amount
demanded by the policy holders
in this financial year.  That is approximately
₹4200 crore.  The formula for calculating the claims paid ratio
is also very simple.  ₹3522
crores which has been given to the policy holders
and the total amount demanded was ₹4200 crores, we will
divide this and multiply it
by 100.  So the claims paid ratio is ₹83.87%
i.e. out of ₹100 demanded by the policy holders, the
company has given ₹84.  How much money has not been
paid?  ₹16 out of 100 ₹16 Company has
denied during the claims.  Now here we
can see that the number of claim settlements is
quite good.  It is more than 97%.
But if we talk about the claim amount, the
claims paid ratio is not as good
as the claim settlement ratio.  Now this
₹16 which the company has refused to pay.
What money could this be?  This
could be all the claims that the company has repudiated
, those that have been rejected, and
also the money that the company has deducted.
Suppose any deduction from any claim be it ₹00, ₹00 or ₹1 lakh is
also included in this amount.  That
means, out of the total amount demanded, the
company has paid only Rs 84.
Now friends, let us understand whether it is good,
bad, average, how is it?  So the
criteria that we have set for the companies is the
same for everyone.  If any company has a
claims paid ratio between 85 to 95 then
it is very good.  That means the
company is giving very good money to its policy
holders.  As we
saw in the case of HDFC Ergo also.  There was a very
good claim spread ratio.
If a company has a claim spread ratio of 80 to 85%, then
we consider it good as it
is above average but not in the very good category.  The
average is 75 to 80% and if someone has
less than 75% then he will be considered to have a poor claims
paid ratio.  Now after seeing this data and these
ratios, many comments come
that Sir, should we change the company?
Should we change?  Should we stay with this company
?  So the purpose of this data is
not to recommend you to change the company
or change the plan.  The purpose of this data is to
give you a realistic picture
of how your company is performing.
If a company is giving out ₹184 then it is
a good amount.  But we want to see how
each company is
performing across the industry compared to its peers.  So that you exactly
know what is the performance of which company.
Like we do in mutual funds.  We
track who is getting what returns and
who is not.  So with this data you will
get the latest and clear picture.
My intention through the Health Insurance Report Card series is not to recommend to you
which company you should go with or which
company you should stay with.  My aim is to
transparently show you
which company is in what position in terms of claims
so that you can compare other factors and
data and take real-time
practical decisions about health insurance.
Now we move on to our
next metric that is Incurred Claim
Ratio ICR.  We have given its weightage
in grading only 15%.  Because
it does not directly impact the policy holder.
But if the
incurred claim ratio of a company is very low then it
means that the company is a little stingy
in giving money.  If there
is too much then it is very lean.  She is
giving money to people generously.  But
ultimately, indirectly, policy holders have to bear the consequences
in the form of higher premiums.  So let us
see what is the
ICR Incurred Claim Ratio of Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company.
Net Incident Claims This
number is taken from their public disclosure document.
That is ₹3190
crore and what is the net earned premium?
₹458.94
i.e. ₹459 crores.  What does it mean?  The net expenses incurred by
this company in this last financial year and the liabilities
incurred on them for
claims are estimated to be ₹3190 crores
and the total premium earned by them
in this entire financial year for this
particular financial year is ₹45859
crores.  If we divide the net added claims by the
total premium earned, that is,
how many claims did this company give for every ₹100 of premium collected, then the number that comes out
is 78.60.
What is the ICR of Aditya Birla? This added
claim ratio of 78.60 is
good or bad. The criteria that we have
set for the companies is between 70 to 85.
Whichever company has an added claim
ratio, it
is beneficial for both the policy holder and the company.  This means
that the company is giving good claims
and they are also getting good money
in the form of premium.  The more it
falls below 70, the more
negative it is for the policy holders.  This means the company
is paying less money and the more it goes above 85, the
more
claims the company is making.  And that will result in
higher policy premiums in the future.
But Aditya Birla's incurred claim
ratio is in the ideal range.  This means that
this ratio is a favorable metric for both the policyholders and the company.  The
next metric,
friends, is the analysis of complaints,
that is, how many complaints were made by the policy holders
and the most important thing about this data is that these are the
complaints made during claims.   There are
complaints regarding some claim.
So the scale at which we will measure this is
10,000 claims.
How many complaints are filed with the company for every 10,000 claims
?  Because what matters most to us is the
claim and
I will also tell you
how many of these complaints were accepted by the company,
which means those policy holders should have
received this claim earlier.  First of all, the
total number of claim related
complaints is
527.  527 complaints related to claims were made throughout the year.
Outstanding complaints of the previous year which were
not resolved even till the end of the last financial year.  There
were 34 such complaints which were
carried forward which you can add in it.
Total claims intimated were
2846356.
These are empty health insurance claims.
And we have to apply this simple formula here,
which will give us the
number of complaints made for every 10,000 claims.  The
total number of complaints was 527, which we will
divide by the total number of claims and
multiply it by 10,000, then the number comes out to be
17.66, which means 18
complaints were filed with Aditya Birla Health Insurance
Company for every 10,000 claims.  Out of these complaints,
150 complaints were fully accepted
which were completely accepted by the company.
1620 complaints were partially
accepted.  That means some terms and conditions were
accepted and
these complaints were partially accepted.  That is approximately
2670 complaints, almost half of the
complaints were accepted by the company.
2300 complaints were totally rejected and
85 complaints are still pending.  But the thing
to notice here is that these 150 complaints
and the 1620 complaints, the
money for these complaints should have been given to the policy holders in the beginning itself
and the figures
show that so many people had to complain to get their
claim money.  Now let us talk about the
number of complaints on this industry, what is this figure?  So, the
criteria that we have set is that if a
company has less than 10 complaints, then it will
come in the excellent category.
If someone has between 10 to 20 complaints, then
we have given him the category of good insurance company.
Not in terms of complaints.  But it
is below the industry average, so we
can consider it a good company and if a
company has between 20 to 30 complaints
then it comes under the industry average
and if it is more than this then it means that
customers face a lot of problems during the claim process.
If we talk specifically about
Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company,
then this number is much bigger than before.
As far as I remember, in the
claims data that we reviewed from 2022 to 25, the
number of complaints might have been around 10 or 12,
but its increase
means that along with more policies and more
business, the complaints in the company are also
increasing.  But if you want to know whether
these complaints are less or more in comparison to other companies.
We have already brought the video of ICICI HDFC.  You
can compare them with them and video report cards of other companies are
coming in the series.  So stay tuned.  If you have
not subscribed to the channel, then subscribe
and also press the notification bell
so that you do
not miss any video of this series in future.  Now friends, here comes
our fifth and final metric which tells us the
speed of claim settlement.   That
is, how quickly this company has
settled the claims of the policy holders.
Within this data, you will see
how many of the total claims filed have been
settled by the company within less than 1 month.  How many claims took one to
three months, how many claims
took three to six months, and
how many claims were settled between six and 12 months.
So out of the total claims,
which
was approximately 29600 claims, 287286
claims, i.e. almost 98, I can say
99% of the claims were settled within a month. The
total number of claims which took one to three months is 2454
and out of the total, this percentage is
approximately 1% of the claims, i.e. 96643 claims were settled between 3 to 6 months.
Five claims took between 6 and 12 months and
11 claims took more than 1 year.
If you look at the percentage of these overall claims,
it is very impressive.
99% of claims are settled in less than a month.
Still, there are 24,000 claims
which took one to three months
and 9,000 claims which took three to
six months.  That means the number of claims of the company
is very large.
Efficiency is quite good at this level.  The company has settled 99% of the claims in
less than a month.
But there is still more
room for improvement here.  If we talk about score
and category, then if more than 95% of the claims of a company are being
settled within a month, then
it is in the excellent category.  The
company which is settling 90 to 95% of the claims
within a month is in the good category.
After that come average and slightly slow
companies.  But Aditya Birla
Health Insurance Company category is
excellent because 99% of claims were settled
within a month.  So after looking at all this data and all the five
metrics, you friends
will notice that the company needs to improve a lot in these two data - claims paid ratio i.e. the
money paid by the company in exchange for the money asked for
and 10,000 claims on complaints.  The
rest of the data of the company is very
good.  If you add up the scores of all these metrics to
arrive at a composite score, the
weighted composite score comes to 88.75,
which
determines the overall grade of Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company and that is very
good.  If this number was more than 90 then the
company would have come in the A Plus i.e. Excellent category.  But as you
saw, the company needs improvement within these two metrics.
So we have given this company a
grade of A and the category is Very
Good.  So friends, this is the
latest claims performance of Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company.
Due to this, the
data of latest claims is not available anywhere.  This is
data till March 31, 2026.  Now,
after looking at these five metrics,
what do you understand about this company?  What
metrics give you an idea of ​​what else
?  You can also share your opinion
with me in the comments.  And
apart from this data, if you have had any personal
experience with this company
regarding claims or any other aspect, then
please share that with me in the comment section.  Let
me know in the comments which company's data you want in the next video in the Health Insurance Report Card 2026 series.
If you want to download a
summarized PDF of the data shown in this entire video,
I have provided its link
in the description and pinned comments of this video.
You can go and download it without
paying a rupee.  And
you can watch the rest of the videos in the Health Insurance Report Card series by
clicking here.  I am
Harvinder Singh, I will meet you in the next video.
Till then take care, stay fit and stay
healthy.  Jai Hind.